Hello, thank you to Dov Weinstock for having me over שבת. Shabbat.
I also just wanted to start by saying thank you there, you
know, so much of the learning that we've been doing is, you
know, it's about that sense about obviously it connects to תפילה tefilla
as much of it does to תענית ta'anit and just yesterday and
I want to say over a bit about it, you know, there
was this whole theme that plays out throughout the מסכת masechet about
the יחיד yachid and ציבור, tzibbur, and, you know, that that earliest
stage the יחידים yachidim are מתענים, mitanim, and the משנה Mishna even
before it spoke about the sense of when you start praying for
rain according to Rabban Gamliel,
you start on the seventh of מרחשון Marheshvan not because he denies
that the third of מרחשון Marheshvan might be the most ideal time,
but כדי שיגיע אחרון שבישראל לנהר פרת kedei sheyagia acharon shebeyisrael lenahar
parat so again it's an interesting inverse of the יחיד yachid and
ציבור tzibbur relationship that the ציבור tzibbur there waits to pray for
rain even if maybe they need it a little bit earlier because
of their concern of even the a few individual stragglers, that's, you
know, and their responsibility towards those. So that's a major theme here
of this מסכת masechet and I did want to say, you know,
that in the last few days I've been sort of like as
I tend to just sort of barreling headlong, thank you, when we
begin the דף, daf, but I really should have and need to
and we will be taking just a moment, you know, to obviously
be משתתף mishtatef in the צער tza'ar and in the of the
חטופים chatuphim and the three teenage boys that are kidnapped. I actually
have a personal connection because my sister who lives in Israel lives
in Tel Mond and one of the boys was from Tel Mond
and two of the boys, one of them from Tel Mond and
one of the others goes to the same high school that my
nephew goes to.
So, you know, really all of our learning and our תפילות tefillot
should be for the for their well-being and that they should be
able to come back safely to their families and we will dedicate,
you know, the learning of our דף daf for that. There's a
just read a תפילה tefilla here. You know what, actually maybe we'll
read the תפילה tefilla at the end of the learning. Can you
forward send that to me? Okay so, all right. So, I do
want to I do want to say that say bring out one
or two things from yesterday before we resume today, which begins at
the beginning of י"א ע"א, yud aleph amud aleph, but I wanted
to bring out some important themes that we will be seeing. One
was, again, this issue that I just said of the יחיד yachid
and the ציבור. tzibbur. On the one hand, you wait to begin
praying for rain the way we פוסקין paskin until the until even
some individuals get all the way back. That responsibility towards the יחידים
yachidim but then the flip of it, which is the next משנה,
Mishna, which is that the יחידים yachidim begin to pray before the
community sort of has it's gone to such a crisis level yet
that the community is not praying but the but the יחידים yachidim
are.
And this issue of who is the יחידים yachidim is an important
question because, again, it's this idea of the, you know, this dynamic
and who's responsible for whom and and so on. So the גמרא
Gemara says that the יחידים yachidim are רבנן, rabbanan, the Torah sages,
although that's a little bit funny why the Torah sages are being
put in this position, and if you think about it, the we
have a particular יחיד yachid that really comes to the surface a
lot in this מסכת, masechet, certainly grabs the imagination, which is חוני
המעגל, Choni HaMa'agel, right, the one who's like the draws a circle
and so many has like this very intimate relationship with God, almost
like sort of like the charismatic, you know, חסיד chasid individual as
opposed to the more institutionalized leadership, but certainly it has nothing to
do with being a Torah scholar. He's not Rabbi Choni, he's חוני
המעגל. Choni HaMa'agel.
And when the גמרא Gemara later talks about who are the יחידים,
yachidim, it talks about it contrasts in a way יחידים yachidim to
the תלמידים. talmidim. The תלמידים talmidim are those that are know Torah,
that, you know, maybe are do not not again rabbis yet but
Torah students, but they are maybe if they want to act as
יחידים yachidim they may, and maybe they're encouraged to and so on
and we had the whole discussion yesterday about יהרא, yohara, would it
be a type of an air religious arrogance for them to be
acting in that role. On the other hand, they're making themselves fast
and it's challenging for them. But the real יחידים yachidim that were
identified were who? And the גמרא Gemara says כל הראויים למנות פרנס
על הציבור, kol hara'uyim limnot parnas al hatzibbur,
somebody who's fit to be a leader. פרנס parnas is like a
lay leader of the community. By the way, the word פרנס, parnas,
לפרנס leparnes
is to, you know, provide sustenance, right? So it's about that sort
of sense of responsibility for the well-being of the community and that's
a very different model. Like it doesn't just mean somebody who's enough
of a Torah scholar to be that, maybe it has nothing to
do with Torah scholar at all. For example, like if you said,
well, we need who's going to be the next president of our
shul, so let's draw up a short list. Okay? So probably the
people you'd put on that short list ראוי למנות פרנס על ציבור,
ra'uy limnot parnas al tzibbur, people that in general, even before they're
in that position, are people that assume responsibility. for the community, have
the capacity and in general are people that are concerned for the
well-being and commit themselves to the well-being of the community. And that's
a very different type of a model of an idea, and those
are the יחידים, yechidim, the people that even before things have hit
the crisis level already see it as their responsibility
to put themselves out and to take steps for the sake of
the well-being of the community. So that seems to be more the
sense of who the יחידים yechidim are, and the fact that the
תורה Torah scholar or the תורה Torah students can aspire to that,
I think does sort of speak about this tension
or this parallel track of תורה Torah leadership and lay leadership. And
the rabbis sort would like to see themselves as the leaders of
the community, but they're also acknowledging that there is such a thing
as lay leadership as well. But it's not really here about, oh,
you're a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, that makes you a holier
person and somebody that should be the יחידים. yechidim. There really is
here this question also about responsibility and I think the and sort
of communal leadership, and that's part of this sort of ongoing issue
here of יחיד וציבור, yachid v'tzibur, yes.
Is there an implication here of a major donor?
Donor? Money? I don't see that.
ראוי למנותו לפרנס rauy lemanoto l'parnas means somebody that has money and
therefore you would make him? I know in contemporary usage, I don't
think so. I don't think in the גמרא Gemara you have that
sense of a major donor. At least, yeah, it's interesting when that
sense comes up, but I don't think so. So anyway, so that's
I think one important theme that comes up here that we'll see
again, we'll see a number of times. The other thing that I
did want to say about this, by the way, was the issue
just very briefly because we have to starting start the דף, daf,
but I can't resist because it was on שבת Shabbat and I
wasn't here, so I wanted to touch on it, was when you
start saying ותן טל ומטר v'ten tal u'matar in בבל. Bavel. So
the גמרא Gemara says sixty days after the תקופה. tekufah. Now you
should know, by the way, that the תקופות tekufot are basically mapped
to the equinoxes and—that work?—the equinoxes and the and the and the
solstice. Just a little quick sort of, so you've got the vernal,
which is spring equinox,
and autumnal, which is fall autumnal equinox, okay? And that's when the
days are exactly twelve hours of dark and twelve hours of sunlight
measured from sunlight, from sunrise to sunset. And then you have the
winter solstice, which is the shortest day of the year, the shortest
amount of sunlight, and the summer solstice, which is the longest day,
the most sunlight. June 21st? What? Yeah.
So these are all basically on the 21st, okay? So this is
September 21st,
December 21st, March 21st, and June 21st. So was that yesterday? Yeah.
Okay, there you go. Okay, anyway, so these are also called in
חז״ל Chazal the תקופות, tekufot, okay? So this is תקופת תשרי, tekufat
Tishrei, okay?
And this is תקופת ניסן, tekufat Nissan,
and I don't know if they—did they call these the תקופות? tekufot?
They do, yeah. It's
תקופת טבת. tekufat Tevet.
Right, it's תקופת טבת, tekufat Tevet, right.
Thank you.
תקופת טבת, tekufat Tevet, right, and תקופת תמוז, tekufat Tammuz, right. Okay,
so those are also called the תקופות. tekufot. So the גמרא Gemara
says that you start praying for rain in בבל Bavel sixty days
after the תקופה. tekufah. Obviously we're talking about סוכות Sukkot and so
on, so we're talking about תקופת תשרי, tekufat Tishrei, and you start
praying sixty days after. That's when they start needing rain in בבל.
Bavel. So sixty days after September 21st gets you approximately November 21st.
You look in your סידור, siddur, what does your סידור siddur say?
November 20th. 20th, whatever, right. I did the exact math, give or
take, whatever, fine. I was off.
Now it's December 4th or 5th. So you take a look in
your סידור. siddur. December
4th, the night of the 4th, right? Exactly, I told you.
Exactly, well, if it's a real old, if it's back before
1900. So the סידור siddur says, what does the סידור siddur say?
December 4th.
4th or 5th.
It says, right, it says through מנחה Mincha December 4th or 5th
if it's a leap year. But anyway, you start saying it December
5th, the night before. How do you get from November 20th to
December 5th? And the answer is... Julian. Exactly. This is November 20th.
חז״ל Chazal were dealing with the Julian calendar. So this is, so
we actually do observe it on, we do switch it on, do
it on November 20th, except we're doing November 20th Julian, which happens
to fall out on December 5th Gregorian. So therefore, we are keeping
not only the date, but we're keeping the date according to the
old Julian calendar. Now, just again for a very brief, very, very
brief explanation,
Julian calendar did know that there were 365 and a quarter days
of a year. So they actually had the regular leap year, etc.,
once every four years. The only problem is, is that it actually
is a little bit less than 365 days a year, and actually
our calendar has... is different, the Gregorian calendar is different than the
Julian calendar in by three days every four hundred years. Okay. Every
three three days, three
three times every four hundred years it does not have a leap
year when the Julian calendar does have a leap year. Basically any
year divisible by one hundred, any exact century although divisible by four
it should have a leap year, it does not have a leap
year the Gregorian calendar unless it's divisible by four hundred. Okay so
that's how you get three days shift every four hundred years, and
so what, big deal, three days every four hundred years, but you
know, a couple enough millennia and it eventually adds up. So by
the time
Pope Gregory came onto the scene, you know, the fact that the
Julian calendar had extra leap days when extra leap years when it
shouldn't have, you know, his like November twentieth, right, was what it
really should have been—I now it's when I start getting into—anyway, it
should have been fewer leap days which would have put the actual
date which would have put the actual date much later. So he
had to add eleven days.
So הלל'ס Hillel's calendar is based on the Julian calendar?
Well no, הלל'ס Hillel's calendar of the, oh you mean about the
adjustment, you know right, shouldn't הלל Hillel have had to have more
adjustment in order to keep things more in sync? And the answer
is yes, okay. So eventually פסח Pesach will stop being in the
spring, I guess given enough time. So anyway so every hundred years
or so this calendar gets, the divergence increases except on a, except
on a year divisible by four hundred. So in the year two
thousand it actually they did not continue to diverge. So that's why
actually it's remained December December fifth between pre-two thousand and post-two thousand,
but in twenty-one hundred we'll start saying it's December sixth because the
years continue to, what?
Let's all remember that.
Let's all keep that in mind, God willing, and let's all live
that long. Anyway, so that's how we get to saying it December,
that's how come it's not only linked to an English date but
the date moves, it's because it's tracking the Julian date. So obviously
that's bizarre that we keep on, since since when do we enshrine
an English date? It's one thing to enshrine something based on a
reality of where the sun is and the seasons and the תקופות,
tekufot, but that's not actually a secular date. So why don't we
just, you know, adjust it? And fine, we'll compute it based on
what we really know the תקופות tekufot are and now start saying
it November twentieth not December fifth. So that's a really good question
which I don't have an answer, I have no good explanation how
come we've enshrined the date as opposed to the days from the
תקופה. tekufah. And the other thing I do want to point out
about this once once we're talking about this and then we will
move on is a point that the ראש, Rosh, a famous תשובה
teshuvah of the ראש. Rosh. The ראש Rosh comes to his שטעטל
shtetel in Toledo. That's where he was in Spain, right? Toledo? Yeah.
So anyway and he sees that everybody there is, it's this period
between סוכות Sukkot and whatever sixty days of the תקופה, tekufah, you
haven't started saying ותן טל ומטר v'ten tal u'matar yet but they
need rain and it hasn't been raining. And everybody there is engaged
in special תפילות tefillot for rain and תעניות ta'aniot for rain, they're
doing everything it says in this מסכת masechet because they need rain
and it's not raining. But guess what they're not doing? They're not
saying ותן טל ומטר לברכה v'ten tal u'matar l'vracha because it's not
yet sixty days after the תקופה. tekufah. And he says I could
not believe it because the גמרא Gemara doesn't say, it's not like
just the בבלי Bavli פסקנ'ס paskens one way, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi פסקנ'ס
paskens another, we פסקן pasken like the בבלי Bavli because the בבלי
Bavli is the more authoritative text. He says it's not about that,
it's about the fact that in בבל Bavel they needed rain at
a different time than they needed in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So
says here in Spain we need rain at a different time than
they need in בבל, Bavel, we need more like they need in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, we need rain earlier and it's not just
this year is an unusual year, every single year we need rain
like much much earlier than sixty days before the תקופה. tekufah. So
he says I פסקן pasken for them that you don't say it
sixty days after the תקופה, tekufah, you say it whenever the date
is when you start, when the, in this land, in this country
when you generally start needing rain. And then he says and I
was צווח ככרוכיא ולא אשגחו בי. tzovei'ach k'kruchiya v'lo ashgechu bi.
I was screeching like a crane and nobody paid attention to me.
So this is very comforting to know that, you know, if a
rabbi ever has a hard time persuading the community about something, like,
he was in good company, like, here it was in their own
best
interest, logically the הלכה halacha was that way, but they were just,
and it was somebody of the stature of the ראש Rosh and
they refused to listen. They were like no this is what we've
always been doing. So they're going to do their תעניות ta'aniot for
rain but they're not going to say ותן טל ומטר. v'ten tal
u'matar. The only remnant of this and להלכה, l'halacha, sadly or whatever,
ironically, you know he, the community won out, we do not פסקן
pasken like the ראש. Rosh. The only echo we have of the
ראש Rosh's position which is a completely logical one is if you're
living in a country which needs rain earlier than sixty days after
the תקופה, tekufah, so you don't say ותן טל ומטר v'ten tal
u'matar but if accidentally you forgot and by accident said ותן טל
ומטר v'ten tal u'matar then you don't have to go back. So
that's the degree to which we פסקן pasken like the ראש. Rosh.
Yes.
So that would seem to imply here where
we need
rain. Interesting, right. So that would simply, yeah, it's
very strange.
And I should just say, let me just end this and then
we'll continue with the גמרא, Gemara, that what this does bring up,
you know, one of the powerful things about this מסכת masechet is
this sense of as we've been talking about rain as demonstrating God's
relationship to the land, God's closeness, God's answering God's, so it doesn't
start raining, it's almost like the מסכת masechet says, you start praying
for rain on זיין מרחשון. Zayin Mar-Cheshvan. If it hasn't rained by
י"ז, Yud-Zayin, here's what you have to do. It's like short time.
Right, but also like, yeah, why hasn't God answered us yet? We
gotta start doing something. But there's this sense that you're דאווענינג davening
and you're expecting a response, the assumption of the efficaciousness of the
דאווענינג. davening. Ten days, right. Ten days, right. Here, it's like why
do we say ותן טל ומטר? v'ten tal u'matar? Because that's what
it says in the סידור. siddur. That's what it says in the
משנה ברורה, Mishnah Berurah, you know? So there's just this sense of
like, okay, this is a liturgy, this is what you say and
so on. And that is really I think like, exacerbated or,
typified by this thing I just said. Like here the ראש Rosh
said we totally need rain earlier, and it's like, but what does
that have to do with what we actually say in the שמונה
עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? If you know, which just says you say December
5th, that's when we say it. Like regardless of what actually... So
the issue about how we shift from a תפילה tefillah and the
sense of the responsiveness and our belief in sort of God's responsiveness
and the way in which this is connected to things that are
happening as opposed to just making it like a fixed
liturgy, you know, you really, that's a shift that you really see
happening. Yeah.
I think we don't appreciate the difference between living in a Mediterranean
climate such as Spain or ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or California to
here. I remember the first time I went to Los Angeles, it
rained the night before, it was mid-September, the previous rain had been
in February. Aha, wow. It is a really big deal and we
don't appreciate what, how, the importance of this. Interesting.
But in the
ראש's Rosh case though, it was in בבל, Bavel, which usually didn't
need much rain, right? It was irrigated by rivers.
Right, right. And that, right, and that's
exactly, exactly, you know, so maybe that's also how it starts becoming
a little bit more of liturgy because of that.
Okay, so
now we have a different understanding of ecosystems like if it doesn't
rain in the winter in California, there's no snow there's no snow,
I mean, right, there's no melt in the spring and that's when
you have the צרות. tzoros.
But it's more about the snow in the winter, right. Interesting. Right.
But again that's an irrigation agriculture system. All right,
so let's now take a look. Now I do so the last
thing I was saying getting back to this theme of יחיד yachid
and ציבור tzibbur and this is what we'll pick up with is
the issue that the גמרא Gemara said and this is what we're
going to be continuing right now is about, you know, the גמרא
Gemara talks about eating in a time
on what, you know, in a time of famine and so on.
And this
whole sort of
playoff from בני יוסף, Bnei Yosef, אחא יוסף, Achai Yosef, excuse me,
three lines from the top on י"א עמוד א'. Yud Aleph Amud
Aleph. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: כל
המרעיב עצמו בשני רעבון, Kol hamar'iv atzmo bishnei ra'avon, anybody who also
causes himself to go hungry in a time of famine, maybe you
have food but you don't want to... I mean it doesn't mean
you starve yourself literally, but you do not, but you know, you
only eat sparingly because you want to identify with the, share in
the suffering of the community. ניצל ממיתה משונה. Nitzal mimitah meshunah. Is
saved from an unusual death, meaning not like a natural unnatural death.
שנאמר: Shene'emar: ברעב פדך ממות, Birav padekha mimavet, in famine God has
redeemed you from death. ברעב, Birav, the גמרא Gemara says מרעב מיבעי
ליה. mi'rav mibaei lei. He has redeemed you from
famine? אלא הכי קאמר: Ela hakhi ka'amar: בשכר שמרעיב עצמו בשני רעבון,
B'sekhar she'mar'iv atzmo bishnei ra'avon, in the merit that somebody is causing
himself to go hungry in a time of famine, ניצל ממיתה משונה,
nitzal mimitah meshunah, is saved from an unnatural
death. So again and here is again this theme that here you
are as a יחיד, yachid, you could separate yourself from what the
suffering of the community, but you choose rather to not just emotionally
but even in your actions act in a way that really places
you
within the, within the tragedy, within the suffering of the community. So
again that יחיד-ציבור relationship is really being, is really being focused on
here. אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Reish Lakish: אסור לאדם Assur l'adam and
now we're going to continue with that. אסור לאדם לשמש מיטתו בשני
רעבון. Assur l'adam leshamesh mitato bishnei ra'avon. Not only about food, a
person should not be having sex during the times of famine. שנאמר:
Shene'emar: וליוסף ילדו שני בנים בטרם תבוא שנת הרעב. U'l'Yosef yuldu shnei
banim b'terem tavo shnat hara'av. He had two children before the period
of famine came, but once the period of famine came he was
no longer. Now does that mean it's a general sort of like
we said before, you know, obviously you could see a parallel here
like the משנה: Mishnah: There's תענית, ta'anit, which is מרעיב עצמו, mar'iv
atzmo, there's אסור בתשמיש המיטה, assur b'tashmish hamitah, so here not having
sex,
and so it's just a way of sort of identifying, of sense
of denying oneself certain pleasures, but also could be, you know, that
bringing more children into the world and more mouths to feed is
also sort of seen as sort of disregarding... suffering that you know
and what is happening around you. תניא בברייתא Tanya ba'braisa חשוכי בנים
chasochei banim משמשים מיטותיהם בשני רעבון. meshamshim mitoseihem bishnei re'avon. Those that
are deprived of children, meaning people that have not yet had kids,
are allowed to have sex during this period. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
So again, that's sort of what Ben was saying a second ago?
What? That's sort of what we just said? No, but again, I
think that that's interesting in terms of that issue of balancing יחיד
yachid and ציבור. tzibbur There's an idea of identifying with the ציבור
tzibur. and so on, but then there's also, you know, particular profound
personal needs sometimes that need to be addressed. So I think that
there is that question of how to exactly strike that balance, you
know? What did you want to say about that? So it's about
the תענוג ta'anug because it's not about the ילודה. yeluda. Uh-huh. But
it's about also the ילודה yeluda because the ילודה yeluda is also
taking money. I mean, children are also... but there are exceptions. Right.
Right. כל העניין של המיניות הוא גם העניין של ההנאה וגם העניין
של הילודה וזה מאוד מסובך כל העניין הזה, נכנסים כאן לאיזשהם. kol
ha'inyan shel ha'miniyus hu gam ha'inyan shel ha'hana'ah ve'gam ha'inyan shel ha'yeluda
ve'zeh me'od mesubach kol ha'inyan hazeh, nichnasim kan le'eizesheh. Right, so thank
you. But but I but what? It's only if you can... I
don't know, it's a good question. But so I think you're right,
but I don't think that it means that the issue of pleasure
and children are intertwined. I don't think it necessarily means that the
only problem of having sex is that of pleasure. Maybe you're right.
I think it could also be just,
you know, bringing more children into the world at
a time like this.
But I also, but what I think is that sometimes you can't
always be worried about the world's problems if you... you know, you've
also got, you know, your personal profound problems that sometimes have to
override. So that's sort of the way I read it is again,
trying to figure out this balance between the individual and the ציבור.
tzibur I think the רש"י Rashi there says it's more of a
technical thing, like because if you still have the מצוה mitzvah of
פרו ורבו, peru u'revu, then you have a... and maybe it's a...
Right, it's just a technical מצוה mitzvah aspect. That, yeah, you could
frame it that way as well. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara continues
like this. Okay. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: בזמן שישראל שרויים בצער ופירש
אחד מהן bizman she'Yisrael sheruyim be'tza'ar u'peirash echad mehen and one of
them separates himself from the community and is not משתתף בצער, mishtatef
be'tza'ar, באין שני מלאכי השרת שמלווין לו לאדם ומניחין לו ידיהם על
ראשו. ba'in shnei malachei ha'shares she'melavin lo le'adam u'manichin lo yedeihem al
rosho. So the two heavenly angels that accompany a person come and
you thought it was only on שבת, Shabbos, but actually according to
other גמרות, Gemaros, it's actually the whole time.
There's actually a little תפילה tefillah you're supposed to say when you
go into the bathroom to tell the angels to wait outside when
you have to go to the bathroom. Serious! Anyway, and they come
and they put their hands on your head ואומרים, ve'omrim, and they
say at this person's head, and they say: פלוני זה שפירש מן
הציבור אל יראה בנחמת הציבור. ploni zeh she'peirash min ha'tzibur al yeira'eh
be'nechamas ha'tzibur. This person that separates himself, he should not see in
the consolation of the community. Which is by the way quite fascinating,
you know, because that's in a way a whole theme about the
beginning of מגילת רות, Megillas Rus, thinking about it. They were literally
פורש מן הציבור poreish min ha'tzibur when at that time and then
they come back and... Anyway, so alright. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, it
says in another ברייתא: braisa: בזמן שהציבור שרוי בצער אל יאמר אדם
אלך לביתי ואוכל ואשתה ושלום עליך נפשי. bizman she'ha'tzibur sharui be'tza'ar al
yomar adam eilech le'veisi ve'ochal ve'eshteh ve'shalom alayich nafshi. So what do
I care?
They're suffering, I'll just go and I have enough money and resources,
I'll take care of myself. ואם עושה כן עליו הכתוב אומר: ve'im
oseh chen alav ha'kasuv omer: והנה ששון ושמחה הרוג בקר ושחוט צאן.
ve'hineh sason ve'simcha harog bakar ve'shachot tzon. Here you are, you're rejoicing,
you're slaughtering sheep and cattle, אכול בשר ושתות יין, achol basar u'shasos
yayin, eating meat and drinking wine. אכול ושתה כי מחר נמות, achol
u'shaseh ki machar namus, eat and drink because tomorrow we will die.
You thought that was just Epicurus? מה כתיב בתריה? mah kesiv basrei?
So this is a guy who's going, he's just, you know, indulging
himself in pleasure. So what does it say afterwards? ונגלה באזני השם
צב-אות אם יכופר העון הזה לכם עד תמותון. ve'niglah be'oznei Hashem Tze-vaos
im yechupar he'avon hazeh lachem ad temusun. This will be revealed to
the ears of God, this sin will not be atoned for you
until you die. So therefore this is a very terrible sin. You
know, the whole point about פורש עצמו מדרכי הציבור
poreish atzmo mi'darchei ha'tzibur is listed amongst those
like אין לו חלק לעולם הבא. ein lo chelek le'olam ha'ba.
That whole sense of sort of identifying, you know, with the community.
I mean one should even point out as well in terms of
the whole question of, you know, punishment and עולם הבא olam ha'ba
and those types of questions, that the פשט pshat of the idea
of somebody getting כרת, kareis, הכרת תכרת, hikareis tikareis, you know, means
separated from the community, right? So you are נכרת מעמך, nichras me'amecha,
you are cut off from your community. So that whole sense of
sort of of your, you know, the ultimate punishment in a way
is this, you know, is about this question about being part of
or cut off from the community. So it's not surprising that, you
know, חז"ל Chazal sort of translated it in terms of עולם הבא,
olam ha'ba, yes. And I was going to say, we've just made
a shift, because we started off by saying that it's a good
thing that you do later, מיצה מצוה מן המובחר. mitzah mitzvah min
ha'muvchar. Now we're saying it's a bad thing if you don't. I
mean, it's becoming more of an imperative. Right, well there it was
about starving yourself, you know, here it's you're actually going and indulging
yourself, you're completely sealing yourself off, you know, you're completely disregarding it.
But it's a good point, the shift of the censure here. Well
the גמרא Gemara is actually about to cover that all. Right. Okay.
Right. Well, well now we're getting even worse. Because עד כאן מידת
בינונים, ad kan middas beinonim, that's only average people, אבל, aval, meaning
you're average bad. אבל במידת רשעים, aval bemiddas reshaim, or whatever, wicked
people, כדכתיב kedichtiv it says, אתו ואקחה יין ונסבאה שכר והיה כזה
יום מחר. esu ve'ekcha yayin venisbe'a shechar vehaya kaze yom machar. So
let's go and take wine and get drunk with mead and it'll
be like this tomorrow. Now how is it really different? It's not
so clear. Rashi says the difference is that earlier it said מחר
נמות, machar namus, that a person really is afraid that they'll die,
as opposed to just סתם stam live it up, reading that more
literal, that he's really afraid. So you're doing it out of fear
that you'll die, that's one thing. Here, the guy just wants to
party all the time, and there's no sense of a fear that
he'll die. That's even more of a רשע. rasha. מה כתיב בתריה,
ma ksiv basreih, what does it say after that? הצדיק אבד ואין
איש שם על לב כי מפני הרעה נאסף הצדיק. hatzadik avad ve'ein
ish sam al lev ki mipnei hara ne'esaf hatzadik. The righteous are
lost and there's nobody paying attention because it's because of the evil
that the righteous have been taken away. So this person's sins cause
even the צדיקים tzadikim in the community to die. And Rashi sort
of says it means and therefore that the צדיקים tzadikim won't be
available to pray for the community. So that's also interesting again about
that יחיד yachid idea, that here's the צדיק, tzadik, the יחיד yachid
that could come to the defense of the community, and because of
the way this individual is separating himself from the community, he impacts
those special individuals that could help the community. אלא, ela, rather יצער
אדם עצמו עם הציבור, yetzayer adam atzmo im hatzibbur, you should participate
with the afflictions of the community, שכן מצינו במשה רבינו, shekein matzinu
beMoshe Rabbeinu, for such as what we find by Moshe, שציער עצמו
עם הציבור, shetzi'er atzmo im hatzibbur, שנאמר, shene'emar, וידי משה כבדים ויקחו
אבן וישימו תחתיו וישב עליה. videi Moshe kveidim vayikchu even vayashimu tachtav
vayeshev aleha. Moshe, they took a rock for him to sit on
during this war against עמלק. Amalek. וכי לא היה לו למשה כר
או כסת? vechi lo haya lo leMoshe kar o kesset? And Moshe
didn't have a pillow or a blanket to sit on? לשב עליה?
leshev aleha? אלא כך אמר משה, ela kach amar Moshe, Moshe said,
הואיל וישראל שרויים בצער, ho'il veYisrael shruyim betza'ar, since the Jewish people
or Israel is in pain and suffering, they're going to war, אף
אני אהיה עמהם בצער, af ani eheyeh imahem betza'ar, even I will
be with them and I will participate in their suffering. So you
don't just stay at home and watch on TV in your nice
comfortable living room, you actually find ways to identify and participate with
this suffering. וכל המצער עצמו עם הציבור, vechol hametzayer atzmo im hatzibbur,
and one who does this, זוכה
ורואה בנחמת הציבור, zocha vero'eh benechamas hatzibbur,
will ultimately see the consolation of the community. ושמא יאמר אדם, veshema
yomar adam, and perhaps a person will say, מי מעיד בי? mi
me'id bi? Who will testify if I go ahead and I do
this in private? Nobody will know. Meaning I can publicly appear to
participate in what the community is doing. This also raises that interesting
question, what does it mean to be part of the community? Is
it just in the obvious visible ways? Or is it here even
in terms of your own emotional internal private ways? So here a
person says, look, when I
go out with the community I'll דאבן daven with them, I'll participate,
even if personally I'm not really feeling anything, and when I go
home
I'll do my own
thing, who's going to testify as to what? Says the גמרא, Gemara,
אבני ביתו של אדם וקורות ביתו של אדם מעידים בו, avnei beiso
shel adam vekoros beiso shel adam me'idim bo, the rocks and the
beams of his house will testify against him. אבני ביתו, avnei beiso,
excuse me, שנאמר, shene'emar, כי אבן מקיר תזעק, ki even mikir tiz'ak,
the rock will call out from the wall, וכפיס מעץ יעננה. vechafis
mei'etz ya'anena. What? וכפיס מעץ יעננה. vechafis mei'etz ya'anena. The כפיס chafis
from the wood will answer him. The כפיס chafis which is like
the pieces of, Rashi says like the stones that you would put
in between the wood to give it stability, that will answer against
him. So what you think is taking place in your house and
private and nobody sees, you will somehow be made, it will be
brought into the public sphere. The very house which signifies the privacy
in which you're trying to separate yourself out, you'll be somehow shamed
publicly. But again, the important point here is the idea that it's
not just about your public behavior which is significant here. דבי רבי
שילא אמרי, debei Rabbi Shila amri, back to the two heavenly angels,
שני מלאכי השרת המלווים לו לאדם הם מעידים עליו, shnei malachei hashareis
hamelavim lo la'adam heim me'idim alav, they testify against you, שנאמר, shene'emar,
כי מלאכיו יצוה לך, ki malachav yetzaveh lach, God will command his
angel against you. I don't know what to read into the whole
focus on the angels here as there should be something more to
be said about this, why all of a sudden we're finding angels
are the ones that kick you out and the angels are the
ones that announce it. I don't really have something profound to say
about that. רבי חלפתא אומר, Rabbi Chalafta omer, נשמתו של אדם היא
מעידה עליו, nishmaso shel adam hi me'ida alav, your very soul testifies
against you, which is like your sinning is really between or your
separating yourself out is at your interior emotional plane or in your
private plane, but ultimately that will speak against you, שנאמר, shene'emar, משוכבת
חיקך שמור פתחי פיך, mishocheves cheikecha shmor pischei ficha, from that that
lies down in your bosom, you should, which is normally interpreted as
your spouse, you should watch what your mouth says. So what? Sorry.
So what? Sorry? Except for Jeff Sterling who passed the ball first.
Oh! Oh there you go. Exactly. But okay right. So ויש אומרים
אדם הוא שהוא מעיד עליו, Veyeish omrim adam hu shehu me'id alav,
excuse me, did I just skip a line? ויש אומרים איבריו של
אדם מעידים בו, Veyeish omrim evarav shel adam me'idim bo, your very
limbs, שנאמר shene'emar אתם עדי נאם השם, Atem eidai neum Hashem, you
are my witnesses, says God. I don't from the context of that
פסוק pasuk I'm not exactly sure how it knows that it means
the limbs, but okay. Yeah, it is plural. I didn't check it,
but there's another אתם עדי Atem eidai which I know, which is
about עבודה זרה avodah zarah and so on, which I didn't remember
to be about the limbs of a person. Anyway, I think this
is interesting about your very soul. Is this basically saying that these
things impact your נשמה, neshamah, meaning are they trying to say that
you think you're doing it in private but ultimately things, you think
you're all the things you're doing nobody knows about, ultimately they'll become
public? People do find out about these things and they do become
publicized. That would sort of be the very house will call out.
Or maybe it's saying they don't become public but it eats away
at your נשמה, neshamah, or it affects your very person. I think
that there could be something being said here other than just some
miraculous way in which it will be, but trying to reflect what
actually will be the consequence. What did you want to say, Seth?
I think it also says something about creating a gap between oneself
and one's עצמות atzmut or being or something. Right, it creates that
gap between who you are and your נשמה. neshamah. Right, right. Right,
right. That's a very good point, that your איברים evarim are the
ones you're indulging in through all this physical pleasure. It's saying it's...
oh, you mean the fact that you're looking so nice and healthy,
that testifies to what you've been doing. Right. But also to shift
from the physical manifestation of this to a more spiritual impact. It
goes through that נשמה neshamah or the מלאכים. malachim. You see it
even affects the external. Right, right. Okay, nice. Where's the פסוק? pasuk?
43:10. אתם עדי נאם השם ועבדי אשר בחרתי למען תדעו ותאמינו לי
ותבינו כי אני הוא לפני לא נוצר אל ואחרי לא יהיה. Atem
eidai neum Hashem ve'avdi asher bacharti lemaan tedu veta'aminu li vetavinu ki
ani hu lefanai lo notzar el ve'acharai lo yihyeh. I don't see
where it's about limbs. It doesn't look like limbs. At least in
פשט. pshat. Yeah, it is about the עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. הנה
הגידו הראשונות ושמעו יציגו עדיהם יצדיקו וישמעו ויאמרו אמת. Hinei higidu harishonot
veshimu yatzigu edeihem yitzdiku veyishmeu veyomru emet. I don't know. Okay, anyway.
Alright, now let's continue. Gemara says like this: אל אמונה ואין עול.
El emunah ve'ein avel. This is from דברים, Devarim, from האזינו. Ha'azinu.
A God of trustworthiness, there is no perversion. אל אמונה, El emunah,
כשם שנפרעים מן הרשעים לעולם הבא אפילו על עבירה קלה שעושים, keshem
shenifra'im min haresha'im le'olam haba afilu al aveirah kalah she'osim, the same
way the wicked get punished in the world to come even on
a small sin, כך נפרעים מן הצדיקים בעולם הזה על עבירה קלה
שעושים. kach nifra'im min hatzadikim ba'olam hazeh al aveirah kalah she'osim. Therefore
the righteous get punished even for a small sin in this world.
This is חז״ל's Chazal attempt, which is also obviously an important thing
to address in מסכת תענית, Masechet Taanit, and it gets touched on
multiple times, which is the whole sense of theodicy and reward and
punishment. The פסוקים psukim say you do the מצוות, mitzvot, ונתתי גשמיכם
בעתם. venatati gishmeichem be'itam. You don't do the מצוות, mitzvot, you get
driven from the land. It doesn't always exactly work out that way.
One of the things by the way that I've been pointing out
is that תענית, Taanit, I think it's noteworthy that in תענית Taanit
it's not the response to lack of rain is oh we sinned
let's do תשובה. teshuvah. Meaning there is תשובה teshuvah mentioned a little
bit when it talks about the public sort of תענית, taanit, but
mostly it's God isn't giving us rain, let's call out to God.
תענית Taanit is a way of intensifying that calling out to God.
In a way some of that whole question of theodicy actually is
not as central as you might think. It's not necessarily linked to
sin in the normal way and about sin and תשובה, teshuvah, it's
about the relationship and if God isn't giving
us rain we have to really work at restoring that relationship. Nevertheless
it is an issue that does come up and חז״ל Chazal are
always worried because or pay attention to the fact that it empirically
doesn't work that way, that the righteous do well and the wicked
suffer. The basic way that חז״ל Chazal deal with it is ascribing
most of
the accounting to עולם הבא. olam haba. In עולם הבא olam haba
it all get equaled. Okay fine it'll get equaled, but why is
it unequal still in this world? Well, because the רשעים resha'im are
doing well because they're getting rewarded for all of their tiny little
מצוות, mitzvot, don't worry, that's a way of clearing the ledger so
they can get fully paid up for their עבירות aveirot in עולם
הבא. olam haba. And the צדיקים tzadikim are having it bad because
they're getting paid up for their עבירות aveirot here so that they'll
be able to get totally rewarded in עולם הבא. olam haba. That's
this idea of אל אמונה. El emunah. וכך נפרעים מן הצדיקים בעולם
הזה על עבירה קלה שעושים. Vekach nifra'im min hatzadikim ba'olam hazeh al
aveirah kalah she'osim. ואין עול, Ve'ein avel, there's no perversion. כשם שמשלמים
שכר לצדיקים לעולם הבא אפילו על מצוה קלה שעושים, keshem shemeshalmim sachar
latzadikim le'olam haba afilu al mitzvah kalah she'osim, the same way they'll
get
their reward in the
world to come, the righteous, אפילו על מצוה קלה שעושים, afilu al
mitzvah kalah she'osim, even the tiny מצוה, mitzvah, כך משלמים שכר לרשעים
בעולם הזה. kach meshalmim sachar laresha'im ba'olam hazeh. even for the small
מצוות mitzvos שעושים she'osim על מצוה קלה שעושים al mitzvah kalah she'osim
צדיק וישר הוא tzadik veyashar hu God is righteous and upright. So
what does that mean? אמרו amru or they take out אמרו, amru,
מלמד melamed that בשעת פטירתו של אדם besha'at ptirato shel adam at
the time that a person passes away לבית עולמו lebeit olamo to
his eternal rest, כל מעשיו kol ma'asav now it's not נפתרים niftarim
which you could understand why he says פטירתו ptirato but it's מפרטים
mifratim from the word פרט prat are enumerated לפניו. lefanav. ואומרים לו
ve'omrim lo and they the angels say to him כך וכך עשית
kach vekach asita look here's what you did במקום פלוני ביום פלוני
bimkom ploni beyom ploni and this place and this place at this
time. והוא אומר הן vehu omer hen and he has to admit
to it. ואומרים לו ve'omrim lo וחתום vechatom sign sign here that
you admit that you've done all these things in your life. וחותם
vechotem and he signs שנאמר ביד כל אדם יחתום shene'emar beyad kol
adam yachtom right in every person's handwriting he will sign. ולא עוד
velo od not only does he admit that he's done all these
things אלא שמצדיק עליו את הדין ela shematzdik alav et hadin he
accepts the justice of the judgment against him ואומר להם ve'omer lahem
יפה דנתוני yafe dantuni you've judged me properly לקיים מה שנאמר למען
תצדק בדברך lekayem mah shene'emar lema'an tizdak bidvarecha you God are found
righteous in your word. It's a pretty scary idea right like when
you die they're going to play you back the movie of your
whole life where everything you did in private everything you did in
public and you're going to have to admit to all of it.
So presumably what that is doing here is that goes back to
the idea of ערב של אדם erav shel adam נשמתו של אדם
nishmato shel adam in the end you yourself will have to testify
against yourself about everything that you have done wrong. But now obviously
we're generalizing it and it's not just about פרישה מן הציבור. perishah
min hatzibur. Yeah so it says אמר שמואל amar shmuel כל היושב
בתענית kol hayoshev bta'anit okay so that was the end of that
whole fascinating thing but again the major theme there is about פרישה
מן הציבור perishah min hatzibur and being משתתף בצער של הציבור mishtatef
batza'ar shel hatzibur again something which is a larger theme here of
יחיד וציבור yachid vetzibur and also sadly very relevant now of course
with all the things that are going on for the חטופים chatufim
and it's easy to not but the imperative of course to really
identify and be משתתף. mishtatef. So the גמרא gemara now continues and
says אמר שמואל amar shmuel so now we get back to the
issues of fasting. כל היושב בתענית נקרא חוטא. kol hayoshev bta'anit nikra
choteh. Anybody who sits in a fast is called a sinner. Okay
we just got through the whole idea the whole מסכת masechet is
about fasting but you're considered a sinner. סבר כי האי תנא דתני
savar k'hai tana detani he opines like the following תנא tana that
we taught. רבי אלעזר הקפר ברבי אומר rabbi elazar hakappar birebbi omer
מה תלמוד לומר וכפר עליו מאשר חטא על הנפש. mah talmud lomar
vechiper alav me'asher chata al hanefesh. This is by a נזיר nazir
he has to atone for him for that he sinned on the
soul. Now the פשט pshat in the פסוקים psukim is first of
all this is only the sin offering that a נזיר nazir brings
when he becomes טמא tameh because he encountered a dead body and
על הנפש al hanefesh means for the dead body in which he
encountered. But that's not the way the גמרא gemara is reading this.
ובאיזה נפש חטא זה אלא שציער עצמו מן היין. uve'eizeh nefesh chata
zeh ela shetzi'er atzmo min hayayin. With what soul did this person
sin? חטא זה chata zeh אלא שציער עצמו מן היין ela shetzi'er
atzmo min hayayin he sinned against his own soul that he deprived
himself from wine. והלא דברים קל וחומר. vehalo devarim kal vachomer. You
can make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה זה שלא ציער עצמו
אלא מן היין umah zeh shelo tzi'er atzmo ela min hayayin this
person that only afflicted himself from withholding wine נקרא חוטא nikra choteh
is called a sinner המצער עצמו מכל דבר ודבר על אחת כמה
וכמה hametzayer atzmo mikol davar vedavar al achat kamah vechamah how much
more so somebody who withholds himself from all things. Now by the
way I do want to say a parenthetical point here that somebody
pointed out to me which was so true and I realized it
is because of a גמרא gemara like this that we identify the
נזיר nazir with like asceticism and it's that ציער עצמו tzi'er atzmo
and it's about denying a pleasure. But it's not so clear that
the issue about wine is about the pleasure of wine it's about
the fact that wine intoxicates and makes you lose your ability to
necessarily think clearly and think and so it's not necessarily the pleasure
aspect. I mean it's not that the נזיר nazir denies all pleasure
he just denies wine. Like normally you'd think about בשר ויין basar
veyayin right so it's only יין yayin and I think that there's
an importance not to let the גמרא gemara reframe that the נזיר
nazir is about asceticism. But nevertheless that's the way it's being read
and saying that here he's a sinner for becoming an ascetic just
about wine how much more so somebody that denies himself all things.
Let's just read a little bit more and the גמרא gemara says
like this רבי אלעזר אומר נקרא קדוש. rabbi elazar omer nikra kadosh.
So as opposed to רבי אלעזר הקפר rabbi elazar hakappar רבי אלעזר
rabbi elazar says he's called holy שנאמר קדוש יהיה גדל פרע שער
ראשו shene'emar kadosh yihyeh gadel pera se'ar rosho holy he will be
the growing of the wildness of the hair of his head. ומה
זה שלא ציער עצמו אלא מדבר אחד נקרא קדוש umah zeh shelo
tzi'er atzmo ela midavar echad nikra kadosh this person that only denied
himself one thing is called holy. המצטער עצמו מכל דבר על אחת
כמה וכמה HaMitza'er Atzmo MiKol Davar Al Achat Kama VeKama and all
the more so somebody who afflicts himself from all things. שמואל, Shmuel,
האי קדוש, Ha'i Kadosh, what does שמואל Shmuel do with the fact
that he's called holy? So the גמרא Gemara says ההוא אגידול פרע
קאי, Hahu agidul perah kai, that means the hair is holy, that
he's not allowed to shave the hair, but it doesn't mean that
he as a person is holy for adopting this practice. ולרבי אלעזר
האי נקרא חוטא, U'le-Rabbi Elazar ha'i nikra choteh, and then he's called
a sinner? No, ההוא דסאיב נפשיה, Hahu desaiyeb nafshieh, that just means
that he became טמא, tamei, the simple sense of the פסוק, pasuk,
not he's a sinner for being a נזיר. Nazir. Now it's interesting
to note of course that this issue about the is asceticism a
positive religious practice, you know, is not something that goes away. I
mean רמב"ן, Ramban, you know on the פסוקים, psukim, says and probably
it's פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim that the, you know, that
the נזיר, Nazir, the reason he brings a sin offering at the
end of the process, here it's talking about the sin offering he
would bring if he became טמא, tamei, but it's because like, you
know, ideally he should have remained a נזיר Nazir his whole life,
you know, and that's like it's his sin to stop being a
נזיר. Nazir. Again, although, you know, whereas רמב"ם Rambam famously quotes this
גמרא, Gemara, רמב"ם בשמונה פרקים, Rambam be-Shemonah Perakim, and he quotes ירושלמי
Yerushalmi which even makes the point stronger and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says
וכי לא דייך מה שאסרה תורה, Vekhi lo dayekha mah she-asrah Torah,
isn't it enough for you what the תורה Torah has forbidden that
you have to go and make more things forbidden for you? You
know that the whole idea of רמב"ם Rambam says that this is
like a sickness that people have got, this idea of asceticism as
a religious practice from the basically from the Christians, you know, and
and that the תורה Torah just wants you to have moderation, you
know, the רמב"ם's Rambam golden mean and control, not be led after
your lusts, but the idea of self-denial as a religious practice, you
know, רמב"ם Rambam says is, you know, is a complete perversion. So
obviously there have been various strands within Judaism about this, but the
point I want to make in this context is that my point
is, in what context are we talking about doing the תענית, ta'anit,
right? Is it about the idea of, you know, what שמואל Shmuel
say, well when you have to do a תענית ta'anit because there's
no rain, yeah you gotta do it, but everybody's considered a חוטא?
choteh? Presumably not, presumably it's one thing when you're doing this because
as I said as a way of intensifying תפילה, tefillah, calling out
to God, it's sort of part of this, you know, part of
the reaching out to God, that's where it's appropriate. But if it's
done as a religious practice in itself that by separating myself from
the world this is something that's going to make me holy, you
know, that's where שמואל Shmuel says no actually that's the נזיר, Nazir,
right? It's not like a sense of this urgency to call out
to God and so on, no, I'm holy. And not only, and
the thing I should mention because again of the theme of יחיד
וציבור, yachid ve-tzibbur, not only is I think I would argue is
the problem that is self-denial and separating from the world a positive
religious value or not, but also if you think about the model
of the נזיר Nazir it's also about me being holier than everyone
else, right? I am going to separate myself out, I'm going to
put myself in this very holy place and not get involved in
these worldly pursuits that everybody else does, so it's actually in a
way the opposite of the משנה. Mishnah. In a way it's interesting,
it's juxtaposed with the פורש מדרכי הציבור, poresh mi-darkhei ha-tzibbur, right? There's
the person who is פורש מדרכי הציבור poresh mi-darkhei ha-tzibbur because he
was indulgent when everybody else was suffering and starving. But you could
also be פורש מדרכי הציבור poresh mi-darkhei ha-tzibbur in the reverse, you're
going to deny yourself when everybody else is living a normal life.
So you could say that that's lovely and that's holy and you're
trying to achieve, but you could also say no, there's an intrinsic
problem there because the whole theme here is about the יחידים yechidim
caring about the ציבור. tzibur. They're praying for the ציבור tzibbur. before
the ציבור tzibbur even prays for itself. They're משתתף, mishtatef, right? To
separate and make yourself holier than the ציבור. tzibbur So I think
that there's a double critique in what שמואל Shmuel is saying. A,
the idea of asceticism itself being a religious practice, and B, the
way in which that's a פורש מן הציבור. poresh min ha-tzibbur. Of
course you have the other strand here in רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar.
Okay, there was a comment? Yeah. Just two comments on שמואל's Shmuel
saying. I understand the הישב בתענית ha-yoshev be-ta'anit as someone who is
constantly or regularly, right, right, fasting, and not just, right, and that's
the way I was sort of describing it as well. It's not
like a one-time type of thing. Right. And also the גמרא Gemara
could have understood this, clearly does not, could have understood this, especially
in the context of the public-private contrast that we just saw, as
someone who is fasting is seen as a sinner, like why are
you fasting? Oh, נקרא, nikra, you must have done something wrong. Ah,
that's interesting. Interesting, and that goes also with the word of נקרא,
nikra, like how he's perceived or called, interesting. There's a similar discussion
in נדרים Nedarim about it, נזיר. Nazir. Yeah, the גמרא, Gemara, yeah,
this thing repeats itself clearly. But I do think it's very powerful
the way it's being used here if you think about it as
the mirror image of the earlier discussion. And also what different meaning
of the fast is, right? Fasting in the context of a communal
need and you know, a communal outcry is one thing. Fasting in
a sense of a self, you know, centered religious sort of, you
know, striving is maybe a very different type of a thing. Yeah,
it is, but you said that the emphasis. here is not on
the תשובה Teshuva aspect. Right. But isn't תשובה Teshuva also working on
our relationship with השם? Hashem? Yeah, but it's in a different way.
Yes, but that's not what's being focused. Meaning I think a normal
approach is that sin separates us from God and we have to
fix the sin in order to go back to God, right? But
then there's also the idea of maybe we don't even know what's
separating us from God, we just know God isn't answering, and we
have to just really, really try to reach out and to call
out or whatever. So it's like somebody is trying, a spouse or
a girlfriend or a boyfriend isn't returning the phone calls, right? How
much is it like, 'I'm sorry for whatever I did wrong,' or
how much is it just to try to restore the connection? So
I think that that's the issue here. All right. All right, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so we just did it.
Okay, ומי אמר רב אלעזר הכי? U'mi amar Rav Elazar hachi? Did
רב אלעזר Rav Elazar really say that the person is holy? והא
אמר רב אלעזר לעולם ימוד אדם לעצמו כאילו. Ve'ha amar Rav Elazar
le'olam yamod adam le'atzmo ke'ilu. Interesting phrase, a person should measure himself,
should see himself כאילו קדוש שרוי בתוך מעיו, ke'ilu kadosh sharuy betoch
me'av, like the Holy is in his stomach. Like talk about this
idea of בצלם אלוקים, be'tzelem Elokim, like God is in you and
the point being that to deny yourself food is to sort of
deny, not take care of your religious responsibilities to your body, to
yourself. It's even more graphic than that, God is, the Holy is
in your stomach, שנאמר בקרבך קדוש ולא אבוא בעיר, she'ne'emar be'kirbecha kadosh
velo avo be'ir, in your very essence, in your very midst is
the Holy. So you obviously have to take care and feed yourself
and shouldn't be denying yourself, right? By the way, there is that
aspect of that I should say, part of the whole question of
asceticism as a religious value does have to do with this question
of a dualism, right? The difference between the physical and the spiritual.
And if you see those things as separate and as competing, then
you want to separate yourself from the physical so you could be
more spiritual. If you see them as much more integrated, human beings
are created בצלם אלוקים, be'tzelem Elokim, and if you read that in
a physical way as well, that somehow the very, again, we try
to avoid that type of a reading because of the associating of
the physical with God, but anyway then it leads to a very
non-ascetic approach. Your body is holy, you have to take care of
your body. So here you see him saying the opposite. So the
גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא דמצי לצעורי נפשיה הא
דלא מצי לצעורי נפשיה. ha de'matzi letzaro'ei nafshieh ha de'la matzi letzaro'ei
nafshieh. It depends on whether you're up to it. If your body
can handle it, then it would be a holy thing, but if
you're actually damaging your body in the process, then it's a non-holy
thing. So that obviously tips the scales in favor of the asceticism
assuming you can manage it, which goes against the I think deeper
theological point of כאילו קדוש שרוי בתוך מעיו. ke'ilu kadosh sharuy betoch
me'av. ריש לקיש אמר נקרא חסיד. Resh Lakish amar nikra chasid. ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish says he, now who is the he here? Presumably
it's the one that fasts, but let's read the פסוק pasuk and
then I'll tell you a different גרסא. girsa. He's called holy. שנאמר
She'ne'emar or חסיד, chasid, right, a righteous, I don't know how to
translate it, pious I think would be the best one. שנאמר גומל
נפשו איש חסד ועוכר שארו אכזרי. she'ne'emar gomel nafsho ish chesed ve'ocher
she'ero achzari. So now that's a very strange פסוק pasuk because literally
the פסוק pasuk is one who takes care of his soul, soul
meaning his body, right, so is a pious man and one who
denies his flesh is cruel. So why does that mean that you're
supposed to be an ascetic? So where do you get that from?
So רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel and actually תוספות Tosafot as well has
a different גרסא. girsa. The גרסא girsa is that somebody who, that
who is called a חסיד? chasid? It's somebody who does not יושב
בתענית. yoshev be'ta'anit. The גרסא girsa is כל המונע עצמו מן התענית
נקרא חסיד. kol hamoneia atzmo min hata'anit nikra chasid. Saying the exact
opposite. It is pious to take care of yourself and not to
actually be in a תענית. ta'anit. אמר רב ששת האי בר בי
רב דיתיב בתעניתא. Amar Rav Sheshet hai bar bei rav de'yatib be'ta'anita.
If you have a תורה Torah student that is sitting in a
תענית, ta'anit, ליכול כלבא שירותיה. leichol kalba sheiruteih. A dog should eat
his meal. Meaning like he's not doing anybody any good. Why? Because
the גמרא Gemara will say, well we'll see, we'll read two more
lines. אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא אין תענית ציבור בבבל אלא תשעה
באב בלבד. Amar Rabbi Yirmiya bar Abba ein ta'anit tzibur be'Bavel ela
Tisha B'Av bilvad. This is a little incongruous to the current topic.
There's no public fast in בבל Bavel except for תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av since בבל Bavel does not need rain. So the whole theme
of this מסכת masechet of public fasts for the sake of rain
never takes place in בבל Bavel and the only thing you would
do in בבל Bavel that would be the severity of a תענית
ציבור, ta'anit tzibur, starting the night before, no sex, no bathing, all
of that would only be תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. But the fasts
of this מסכת masechet of rain are not happening in בבל. Bavel.
Now that has I don't know what that's doing in the middle.
Now we'll get back to the last line which will sum up
our earlier discussion. אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Reish Lakish: אין תלמיד חכם
רשאי לישב בתענית. Ein talmid chacham rishai leishev b'ta'anis. This is going
back to let a dog eat his food. A תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham cannot sit in a תענית ta'anis מפני שממעט במלאכת שמים, mipnei
shemema'et b'mlechet shamayim, because it comes at the expense of the more
important religious pursuit of learning תורה. Torah. So this is not saying
that that is intrinsically not a religious pursuit, but what is it
coming at the expense of? There are other religious pursuits which are
more important. So again, the fascinating question about the value of a
תענית, ta'anis, not in the context of תענית ציבור, ta'anis tzibur, about
תענית יחיד, ta'anis yachid, but not יחידים yechidim being מתענה mitaneh for
the ציבור, tzibbur. being מתענה mitaneh for themselves, and to what degree
is that a positive or a negative? Okay, let's end with a...